Inventory of the Papers of Hardy Cross Dillard
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
- Notes: Miscellaneous 1957, 1980, n.d., 3 folders (Box 27)
- Notes: Miscellaneous Book Extracts n.d. (Box 27)
- Notes: "Miscellaneous References" n.d. (Box 27)
- Notes: "Political Questions"--Law and Diplomacy n.d. (Box 27)
- Notes: "Scribblings" n.d. (Box 27)
- Notes: "Televised Wisecrack" n.d. (Box 27)
- Notes: "Various Quotes and Aphorisms" n.d. (Box 27)
- Contracts; Cases on Contracts n.d. (Box 27)
- Equity Jurisprudence; Code Pleading; Common Law Pleading; Virginia Pleading; Constitutional Law; Practice 1925-26 (Box 27)
- Federal Procedure 1927 (Box 27)
- Gradebook n.d. (Box 27)
- International Law; Legal Bibliography 1932, n.d. (Box 27)
- International Relations n.d. (Box 27)
- Law of Partnership; German Grammar n.d. (Box 27)
- Legal History; Review for Bar Exam 1927 (Box 27)
- Notes on various subjects taken at the University of Paris 1930-31, 2 books and loose pages (Box 27)
- Private Corporations 1926 (Box 27)
- Real property 1925-26 (Box 27)
- Torts; Bailments 1925 (Box 27)
- Wills 1926 (Box 27)
- NATO Defense College 1957-58 (Box 28)
- NATO War College 1951 (Box 27)
- Nuremberg: Clippings 1945 (Box 28)
- Nuremberg: Eichman--Notes and Documents 1946-69 (Box 28)
- Nuremberg: Notes and Documents 1942-60, 2 folders (Box 28)
- Offer and Acceptance [J. H. Mudd c/0 HCD] n.d. (Box 28)
- Order of the Coif 1955-56 (Box 28)
- Pending Matters 1969 (Box 28)
- Personal: Army Data 1942 (Box 29)
- Personal: Biographical Data 1947-81 (Box 29)
- Personal: Correspondence 1925-1981, 80 folders (Box 29-37)
- Personal: J. H. Dillard Estate 1946-59 (Box 37)
- Personal: A. L. Dillard Estate 1950-58, 2 folders (Box 37)
- Personal: H. C. Dillard Fan Mail 1967 (Box 37)
- Personal: J. H. Dillard 1968 (Box 37)
- Personal: H. S. Dillard 1952 (Box 37)
- Personal: Expenses 1962; 1965-69 (Box 37)
- Personal: Family Matters 1955-56 (Box 37)
- Personal: Park Hill Rental 1953-1954 (Box 38)
- Personal: Records 1924-81, n.d. (Box 38)
- Personal: Rugby Road Fire 1954-65 (Box 38)
- Personal: Underhill, Lewis K. 1946 (Box 38)
- Phi Beta Kappa 1948 (Box 38)
- Pittsburgh Seminar 1957 (Box 38)
- Potter, William S. 1966-69 (Box 38)
- Practice: Afroyim v. Rusk 1966 (Box 38)
- Practice: Almond v. Day 1955 (Box 38-39)
- Practice: Charlottesville City Code n.d. (Box 39)
- Practice: Connecticut Valley Enterprises v. U.S. 1961-62 (Box 39)
- Practice: Honeywell v. Arlington A.C. Co. 1956, 2 folders (Box 39)
- Practice: Knud-Neilson v. Monika Grimm 1977 (Box 39)
- Practice: Lukens Steel Co./United Steelworkers 1947 (Box 39)
- Practice: Maryland Shipbuilding v. Martin Marietta 1963-64 (Box 40)
- Practice: Roanoke Minimum Wage Schedules n.d. (Box 40)
- Practice: WCHS-TV 1957 (Box 40)
- Practice: Taiwan Fertilizer v. HRI 1959 (Box 40)
- Practice: Terrell Case 1949-51 (Box 40)
- Publications: Reading Guide 1948 (Box 40)
- Ramazani, Rouhollah 1953-54 (Box 40)
- Requests to speak, write, attend, etc 1969 (Box 40)
- Ribble-Gooch File [Restricted] 1965 (Box 40)
- Ritchie, John 1963 (Box 40)
- Robertson, Willis 1963 (Box 40)
- Rogers, Frank 1968 (Box 40)
- Russia 1945-46 (Box 41)
- School of Military Government (SMG)--Clippings 1942, -43, -46 (Box 41)
- SMG--Correspondence 1941-42 (Box 41)
- SMG--Memoranda 1942 (Box 41)
- SMG--Lectures 1942-43 (Box 41)
- SMG--"Rogers Report" 1942 (Box 41)
- Segregation 1955-65 (Box 41)
- Service Academy Board: Social Science Panel 1949 (Box 41)
- Seven Society 1968 (Box 41)
- Sforza Correspondence 1940-41 (Box 41)
- Sovereign Immunity n.d. (Box 41)
- State Department 1965-69 (Box 41)
- Student Recommendations 1934-41 (Box 41)
- Teaching Materials: Contracts 1930-68, 46 folders (Box 46-48)
- Teaching Material: International Law 1930-69, 47 folders (Box 46-48)
- Teaching Materials: Jurisprudence/Legal Philosophy 1930-61, 39 folders (Box 48-50)
- Teaching Material: Public Corporations 1930-68, 3 folders (Box 51)
- Teaching Material: Miscellaneous 1931-69, 21 folders (Box 51-53)
- Thank-you Cards n.d. (Box 53)
- The Research Group: Research Materials 1977 (Box 53)
- Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands 1964 (Box 53)
- Tucker Lecture at Washington and Lee Law School 1967 (Box 53)
- UN-Foreign Relations n.d. (Box 53)
- UNESCO 1967-69 (Box 53)
- U.S. Department of Labor: Foundry Committee 1941 (Box 54)
- U.S. Military Academy: Class of 1924 1965 (Box 54)
- U.S. Naval Academy 1949 (Box 54)
- University of Pittsburgh Chancellor Inauguration 1957 (Box 54)
- University: General 1968 (Box 54)
- Virginia Bar Association 1947-79, 5 folders (Box 54)
- Virginia Bar Association: Annual Meeting 1967 (Box 54)
- Virginia Bar Association: Committee on Legal Conferences 1947 (Box 54)
- Virginia Bar Association: Executive Committee 1968-69 (Box 54)
- Virginia Bar News 1961-63 (Box 54)
- Virginia Episcopal School (VES) 1963-69 (Box 54)
- VES: Board of Trustees 1955-60 (Box 54)
- VES: Board of Trustees--Headmaster Search 1955-61 (Box 55)
- VES: Executive Committee 1954-55 (Box 55)
- VES: Race Policy 1956-59 (Box 55)
- VES, Woodbury, St. Anne's 1956-66 (Box 55)
- Virginia Journal of International Law(VJIL) 1968 (Box 55)
- VJIL: Salute to Dillard 1968 (Box 55)
- Virginia Law Review 1957-61 (Box 55)
- Virginia Quarterly Review 1947-69, 3 folders (Box 56)
- Visitors' Lectures 1940-41 (Box 56)
- Weigert, Hans 1952 (Box 56)
- Wechsler, Herbert 1960, 1977, n.d. (Box 56)
  Printed material and notes
- West Point Student Conference on Foreign Affairs 1952 (Box 56)
- William and Mary 1950 (Box 56)
- Williamsburg International Assembly 1964-65 (Box 56)
- Willrich, Mason 1968 (Box 56)
- Wolfers, Arnold 1946, 1951-52 (Box 56)
- Woltz to Shannon Memorandum 1964 (Box 56)
- Woodrow Wilson School of Foreign Affairs 1948-50, 2 folders (Box 56)
- World Peace Foundation 1935-36 (Box 56)
- World Peace through Law Committee 1963-68 (Box 56)
- Yale Offer 1955-56 (Box 56)
- Speeches
  - Air War College: Notes 1963 (Box 57)
  - Alumni--Washington, D.C. 1964, -68, -72 (Box 57)
  - Alumni--New York: Notes 1979 (Box 57)
  - Alumni: Notes and Drafts 1964-66 (Box 57)
  - Alumni Dinner: Remarks and Introduction of Monrad Paulsen 1968 (Box 57)
  - American Association of the Netherlands: Notes 1973-74 (Box 57)
  - "The American Democracy and World Affairs" 1955 (Box 57)
  - "American Foreign Policy in a Post-Munich World" n.d. (Box 57)
  - "American Law and the Legal Order--Theorectical Framework" [1953] (Box 57)
    Lecture given in Germany
  - American Law Institute: Notes 1970 (Box 57)
  - American Society of International Law (ASIL): Notes 1963-67 (Box 57)
  - ASIL--Annual Meeting: Notes 1963 (Box 57)
  - ASIL: Notes 1970, n.d. (Box 57)
  - ASIL: Notes 1973 (Box 57)
  - ASIL: "Remarks" by HCD at 75th Meeting 1981 (Box 57)
  - Armed Forces Staff College: Notes 1954-63; 72 (Box 57)
  - Army War College: Notes 1954, 61 (Box 57)
  - Association of American Law Schools: "Appointment Dilemmas" 1963 (Box 57)
  - "Base of American Foreign Policy" 1949 (Box 57)
  - Battle (William) Banquet 1964 (Box 57)
  - "The Bricker Amendment" 1954 (Box 57)
  - Brussels--"Cercle des Jurists": Notes 1971 (Box 57)
  - "C & G" Staff College: Notes 1966 (Box 57)
  - Canadian Defense College 1957 (Box 57)
  - "The Changing Nature of International Conflict" 1954 (Box 57)
  - Charleston Speech Notes 1946; 1958 (Box 57)
  - Charlottesville--Albemarle Bar Association 1973; 1977 (Box 57)
  - [China Speech] [1945] (Box 57)
  - "The Civil Rights Bill--Some Abstract Observations" 1963 (Box 57)
  - Class of '38 Reunion 1968 (Box 57)
  - Class of '40 Twenty-fifth Reunion 1965 (Box 57)
  - Class of '65 1965 (Box 57)
  - Classes of '66 and '67 1966, -67 (Box 57)
  - Club du Jendi: NOtes 1975 (Box 57)
  - Command Staff College Speech 1966 (Box 57)
  - "Conference" [?]: Notes 1977 (Box 57)
  - "Conflict and Change--The Role of Law" 1963 (Box 57)
  - "Confusion and Consensus" [University of Baltimore Commencement] 1968 (Box 57)
  - "The Constitutional Framework of U.S. Foreign Policy" 1952-55, 3 folders (Box 58)
  - Cooper Union Address [1938] (Box 58)
  - "The Covenants of Human Rights--Conflicting Views" 1953 (Box 58)
  - Covington and Burling 1972 (Box 58)
  - Cuba Speech n.d. (Box 58)
  - "The Current Role of the State in International Affairs" 1959, -60 (Box 58)
  - Dillard Testimonial Dinners: Notes 1970, n.d., 2 folders (Box 58)
  - "The Dimensions of Learning in a Free Society" 1957 (Box 58)
  - [Dissenting Partner?] n.d. (Box 58)
  - Egypt Speeches: Notes 1962 (Box 58)
  - "Ely Lauterpacht's paper..." n.d. (Box 58)
  - "The Enduring Mission of a Law School--Some Reflections" n.d. (Box 58)
  - Engineering School Lectures 1956, -60, n.d. (Box 58)
  - "Federal Protection, Civil Rights": Notes 1954 (Box 58)
  - Fletcher (Walter) Speech 1966 (Box 58)
  - "Foreign Policy and Germany" 1948 (Box 58)
  - Foreign Service Institute: Notes 1961 (Box 58)
  - "The Function of International Law in International Relations" 1960 (Box 58)
  - Germany Lectures Delivered in Germany: Notes and Outlines 1953, 3 folders (Box 58)
  - Germany Lectures Delivered at U.Va.: Notes 1950 (Box 58)
  - "Government as an Element of Power" 1956 (Box 58)
  - Hague Lectures: Notes and Drafts 1957-58; -73 (Box 58)
  - Harvard Law School Association of Europe: Notes 1971 (Box 59)
  - "The Higher and the Lower Learning" 1939; -53 (Box 59)
  - "Hillel": Notes 1957 (Box 59)
  - Honor Lectures Delivered at UVa and the Air Force Academy: Notes 1947-1970; n.d., 3 folders (Box 59)
  - Humor: Notes and Anecdotes [1958] (Box 59)
  - "Improving Legal Education" n.d. (Box 59)
  - "India's Application--Some Preliminary Observations" n.d. (Box 59)
  - "Insurrection in East Germany" n.d. (Box 59)
  - "International Conflict and Means of Resolution" 1955 (Box 59)
  - "International Law and Some Contemporary Problems"--Delivered at W & L 1967 (Box 59)
  - "Interpretation and Measurement" n.d. (Box 59)
  - [Iran]--"Suggested Remarks" n.d. (Box 59)
  - Jefferson High School: Notes n.d. (Box 59)
  - "Jefferson Today" n.d. (Box 59)
  - Jefferson's Birthday--Delivered at Monticello 1952 (Box 59)
  - John Bassett Moore Society: Notes 1979 (Box 59)
  - John Bassett Moore Society--"The Role of Law in the Cold War": Notes n.d. (Box 59)
  - Judge Advocate General (JAG) Addresses 1950-65 (Box 59)
  - "Jurisprudence or Legal Philosophy" n.d. (Box 59)
  - "Jurisprudencia" [Speech in Spanish] n.d. (Box 59)
  - "Law and Conduct of International Relations" 1953 (Box 60)
  - "Law and Diplomacy" [1950's]; n.d., 2 folders (Box 60)
  - "Law and Fallacies" [Fragments] n.d. (Box 60)
  - "Law and Foreign Policy" [1950] (Box 60)
  - "Law and Logic" 1969 (Box 60)
  - "Law and Moral Problems" 1958 (Box 60)
  - Law Day Speech n.d. (Box 60)
  - "Law, Diplomacy and Conflict": Notes 1959 (Box 60)
  - "Law, Policy and the World Court--Some Suggested Misconceptions" n.d. (Box 60)
  - "The Law School and International Law" 1947 (Box 60)
  - Law School Speeches 1949-64 (Box 60)
  - Law Students--Delivered to Incoming Class 1977 (Box 60)
  - Law Wives--Notes 1947, -55, -57 (Box 60)
  - "Lillich" [?]: Notes 1978 (Box 60)
  - "Logic, Wisdom and the Honor System" n.d. (Box 60)
  - Marine Corps Scholars: Notes 1965 (Box 60)
  - Medical School Lectures: Notes and Outlines 1956-69 (Box 60)
  - Michael Ceremony--Remarks on J. Harry Michael's Elevation to the Bench 1980 (Box 60)
  - "Military Government" 1950-60, 3 folders (Box 60)
  - Mooers Lecture--American University 1977, 2 folders (Box 60)
  - National War College Lectures 1948-61, 2 folders (Box 60)
  - Naturalization Ceremony at Monticello 1963 (Box 60)
  - Naval Academy: Notes 1949 (Box 60)
  - Naval War College: Notes 1960, n.d. (Box 60)
  - Neutrality Issue: Notes 1939, n.d. (Box 61)
  - New York Symposium: Notes 1971 (Box 61)
  - [ROTC]: Notes 1952 (Box 61)
  - Phi Beta Kappa--Delivered at William and Mary: Notes 1950 (Box 61)
  - "Power and Persuasion: The Complex Role of Military in Government" n.d. (Box 61)
  - "Presentation of Portrait of Armistead Mason Dobie" 1965 (Box 61)
  - Princeton: Notes 1950 (Box 61)
  - "Public Policy and Private Preference" n.d. (Box 61)
  - "The Quest for Learning"--Delivered at Norfolk Academy 1964 (Box 61)
  - "Rational Decision-Making and the Segregation Issue" n.d. (Box 61)
  - "Raven Society [and Higher Education]" 1955 (Box 61)
  - "Reflections of an Antique Professor turned Baby Judge"--Delivered at the Friedman Banquet at Columbia 1979 (Box 61)
  - "Relative Values--English and American Systems of Legal Education"--Delivered at Southeastern Conference of AALS 1960 (Box 61)
  - Ribble Tribute [1963] (Box 61)
  - "Richmond": Notes 1947 (Box 61)
  - Richmond Kiwanis 1955 (Box 61)
  - "The Rise of the Nation State and Nationalism" n.d. (Box 61)
  - "The Role of Law" 1949 (Box 61)
  - "The Role of Law in International Relations" 1980 (Box 61)
  - "The Rise of Law in Resolving Conflict" n.d. (Box 61)
  - "The Role of ICJ--Manifestations of Concern" n.d. (Box 61)
  - "The Role of the Nation-State in International Affairs" 1958 (Box 61)
  - "Rotary": Notes 1979 (Box 61)
  - School of Military Government: Notes 1946 (Box 61)
  - School of Business Administration: Notes 1959 (Box 61)
  - Speech at Sons of the American Revolution 1958 (Box 61)
  - "The State, Law and Diplomacy in Today's International Affairs" 1962 (Box 61)
  - "Structure of the Modern State"--Delivered at the Brookings Institution 1954 (Box 61)
  - "The Treaty-Making Controversy" [re Bricker Amendment] [1954?] (Box 61)
  - "Trials and Tribulations of Courts and Lawyers--Judicial Creativity and the Law" 1968 (Box 61)
  - "The University and Contemporary Strains" 1953 (Box 61)
  - University of Cincinnati Law School: Notes 1970 (Box 61)
  - University of Georgia Law School: Notes 1966 (Box 61)
  - University of Pennsylvania Law School: Notes 1964 (Box 61)
  - Vietnam: Notes 1963-65 (Box 62)
  - Virginia Bar Association: Notes 1973 (Box 62)
  - Virginia Bar Association: "The Battered Image of the Lawyer" 1979 (Box 62)
  - Virginia Journal of International Law: Notes 1977, -79 (Box 62)
  - Virginia Trial Lawyers of Association 1980 (Box 62)
  - "A Visitor Looks at Columbia" 1962 (Box 62)
  - Washington Institute of Public Affairs 1971 (Box 62)
  - Wechsler (Herbert): Draft of Speech n.d. (Box 62)
  - West Point Talk on Nationalism 1948 (Box 62)
  - "West Germany and the West" n.d. (Box 62)
  - "Widening Access to the ICJ" n.d. (Box 62)
  - William and Mary Speeches 1980; n.d. (Box 62)
  - "The World Court:--Delivered at Society of the Cincinnati in Richmond 1973 (Box 62)
  - "The World Court: An Insider's View" 1971; n.d. (Box 62)
  - "The World Court--Retrospect and Prospect" n.d. (Box 62)
  - "The World Court: Some Reflections of a Professor Turned Judge" n.d. (Box 62)
  - World Court Speeches: Notes and Fragments of Drafts n.d. (Box 62)
  - Speech Fragments [1960's] (Box 62)
  - Miscellaneous Unidentified Speech: Notes n.d. (Box 62)
- Articles
  - "The Anatomy of Problems of Communication" n.d. (Box 63)
  - China, the United Nations and United States Policy 1966-67, 3 folders (Box 63)
  - "The Comity of Nations" 1957 (Box 63)
  - "Comment on Humanities and the Law" 1964 (Box 63)
  - "Comment on Koessler Article: The International Law on Belligerent Espionage" n.d. (Box 63)
  - "Comment on N.Y.U. Policy Paper Dealing with... Rhodesia" n.d. (Box 63)
  - "Continuing Legal Education: Around the Country.. ." 1969 (Box 63)
  - Functionalism 1942 (Box 63)
  - "Hints on Writing and Research" 1953 (Box 63)
  - "The Judge Advocate General and His Environment" 1952 (Box 63)
  - "Law and Learning" 1963 (Box 63)
  - "The Law and Nations" n.d. (Box 63)
  - "Law, Policy, and the World Court" n.d. (Box 63)
  - "A National Bar Examination--Tentative Appraisal" 1966 (Box 63)
  - "The Policy-Oriented Approach to Law--Some Questions" [1960's], 7 folders (Box 63-64)
  - "Public Policy and Private Choice" n.d. (Box 64)
  - "The Responsibility of Law Teachers in a Time of Challenge" 1964 (Box 64)
  - "Revolution, Recognition and Representative: Current Dilemmas" and variations [article(s) about China] n.d. (Box 64)
  - "The Role of the Institute of Public Affairs" 1951 (Box 64)
  - "Some Aspects of Law and Diplomacy" 1957; 1978, 2 folders (Box 64)
  - "Suggested Topics" [on International Law] n.d. (Box 64)
  - Unidentified Article n.d. (Box 64)
  - Unidentified Article--Footnotes n.d. (Box 64)
  - Abortive Articles n.d. (Box 64)
- Book Reviews
  - Biddle, Francis. The World's Best Hope c. 1948 (Box 64)
  - Bradley, Can We Stay Out of War and Thomas, War: No Glory, No Profit, No Need [1936] (Box 64)
  - Deutsch, Eberhard: HCD's discussion of his book in a letter to ED 1978 (Box 64)
  - Dulles and Armstrong, Can We Be Neutral? [1936] (Box 64)
  - Dunn, Frederick Sherwood. The Protection of Nationals ca. 1932 (Box 64)
  - Harley, John Eugene. International Understanding ca. 1932 (Box 64)
  - Howe, Mark deW. Holmes-Pollock Letters n.d. (Box 64)
  - Kennan, George. American Diplomacy 1951 (Box 64)
  - Pufendorf, Samuel. Elementorum Jurisprudentiae Libri Duo c. 1932 (Box 64)
  - Schacter, Oscar. Sharing the World's Resources 1980 (Box 64)
  - Schacter, Oscar. The Just Sharing of Global Resources 1977 (Box 64)
  - Stone and Simpson. Law and Society [1949?] (Box 64)
  - Von Mehren, A. T. The Civil Law System [1957] (Box 64)
  - Wormser, Rene. The Law: The Story of Lawmakers... [1949] (Box 64)
  - Correspondence and Notes re Book Reviews 1948-50 (Box 64)
  - Notes for Articles and Book Reviews c. 1932 (Box 64)
- Oversize
  - Government/Military Charts for the U.S., China, and the Allied Powers 1945-47, 5 charts
  - Maps of France (with annotations), Germany, China, Asia and the world 1938, 13 maps
  - German poster announcing a lecture by HCD, "Die verfassungmassigen Grundlagen der amerikanischen Aussenpolitik" [1953?]
  - Copy of the "Translation of the Magna Charta" n.d.
- Photographs
  - HCD and other officers aboard the U.S.S. Randolph, along with picture of the Randolph[?] c. 1945
  - HCD with F. D. G. Ribble and John Ritchie Early 1950's
  - HCD at various war colleges 1962, -66, -67
  - HCD lecturing to a group [1964?]
  - HCD delivering lecture [1964?]
  - HCD with a group of students [1964?]
  - HCD with two unidentified women 1968
  - HCD with Senator William Spong and Dean Monrad Paulsen 1968
  - HCD in World Court robe c. 1970
  - Class of '27 with their wives [1960's]
  - Class of '29 with HCD and F. D. G. Ribble 1959
  - Law School Faculty [1965?]
  - Unidentified group of men including HCD, A. E. Dick Howard and Dan Meador n.d.